<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first day of the worldes creation: or of the first weeke of that most Christian poet, W. Salustius, Lord of Bartas</title>
            <title>Sepmaine. Day 1. English</title>
            <author>Du Bartas, Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur, 1544-1590.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11401</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110825</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846293</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846293</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11253</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11401)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11253)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 550:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first day of the worldes creation: or of the first weeke of that most Christian poet, W. Salustius, Lord of Bartas</title>
                  <title>Sepmaine. Day 1. English</title>
                  <author>Du Bartas, Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur, 1544-1590.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 41, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By I. Iackeson, for Gregorie Seaton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of the first day of: La sepmaine.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The first day of the first weeke of du Bartas.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis --  History of Biblical events --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11253:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11253:1"/>
            <p>THE FIRST DAY OF THE WORLDES CREATION: Or Of the firſt weeke of that moſt Chriſtian Poet, W. SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LVSTIVS, Lord <hi>of Bartas.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Etſi ſerò ſeriò.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London, by <hi>I. Iackeſon, for Gregorie Seaton.</hi> 1595.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11253:2"/>
            <head>The Tranſlator to the Author.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SO, ſo, Lord Bartas, ſhould all Arts be ſpent</l>
               <l>In truthes aduauncement, and their Authors glorie:</l>
               <l>Bluſh Christian Poets, to ſeeme eloquent,</l>
               <l>In ſetting foorth a lewd, and lying ſtorie:</l>
               <l>Let Poets learne the ſacred truth to write:</l>
               <l>And Heathens take the lying Epithite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There, there, Lord Bartas hath the truth hir grace,</l>
               <l>Where God is Phoebus, and his ſprite the muſe,</l>
               <l>Where Poets follow Prophets heauenly trace,</l>
               <l>And Parnaſe mount for Zion do refuſe:</l>
               <l>Let heathniſh paraſites that cog and flatter,</l>
               <l>Call fained muſes, to their forged matter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then, then, Lord Bartas art and truth accord,</l>
               <l>When truth is miſtreſſe, and thoſe arts hir maides,</l>
               <l>When ſubtill quirks, and questions be abhord,</l>
               <l>And damſels follow where their miſtreſſe leades.</l>
               <l>Truthes Poets, let them not be vaine diſputers:</l>
               <l>But take hir Prophets for their onely tutors.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus, thus, Lord Bartas hast thou done, and wonn</l>
               <l>Arts garland, and truthes heauenly bleſſing,</l>
               <l>She was thy dittie, God did ſet thy tune,</l>
               <l>His ſprite did guide thee in that truthes expreſſing:</l>
               <l>Now whiles thy works in Fraunce affoord a ſunſhine,</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe this ſhadow may be Englands moonſhine.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11253:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Worſhipfull, wiſe, and learned, M. Anthonie Bacon: perfect health of bodie, increaſe of</hi> vertues and worſhip; to the honorable ſeruice of his countrie, the aduancement of Religion, and the euerlaſting felicitie of his owne ſoule.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our long experience, both of the French eſtate, &amp; language (Right worſhipfull:) the report of your wiſdome bloſſomed in youth, and ripened in yeeres, increaſed by learning at home, and confirmed by trauaile abroad, haue drawne me, a poore nameles countriman of yours, to make choyce of your woorthie title to countenance the forefront of this frame: and your iudgement to cenſure the priuie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiances thereof. The peece of worke which I offer to your patronage and iudgement, was vndertaken in the nonage of my ſtudies, before I was profeſſed, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps had beene ſmothered from the world as an abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, had not ſome my deere friends weaned it from my hands, and foſtered it in their affectionate boſoms, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing it life and light, if not with me, without me: yet not in reſpect, either of the matter which is heauenly, nor the Author which is excellent, deſired I to ſilence my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantlike pen from proceeding heerin: but bicauſe this moſt Chriſtian Poet, and noble <hi>Frenchman Lord of Bartas,</hi> might haue been naturalized amongſt vs, either by a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall act of a Poeticall Parliament: or haue obtained a kingly tranſlator for his weeke (as he did for his Furies:<note place="margin">The king of Scots tranſlated his Furies.</note>) or rather a diuine <hi>Sidney,</hi> a ſtately <hi>Spencer,</hi> or a ſweet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell</hi> for an interpreter thereof. For ſo was I put in a falſe hope by ſome, that the liuing Pen of that worthie decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed knight, had amongſt other his charitable legacies bequeathed a rich ſuit, after our beſt Engliſh faſhion, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:11253:3"/>this honorable Poet: and therefore ſuppreſſed my ragged weeds, till I perceiued their promiſe ſhrunke, &amp; my expectation ſtill naked. And yet if any of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Heroicall Spirits haue vndertaken the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of that act, I would not haue my ſeelie daies worke to preiudice their Weeke, nor my moat to flutter in the preſence of their bright beames: wherefore though my raſh quill hath tooke a further flight into this tranſlation: yet haue I pinioned vp the reſt of hir fethers, and ſuffered onely the firſt daies worke to paſſe abroad: till I may vnderſtand whether any of thoſe ſweete recording Swans haue waded in the deriuation of theſe ſtreames or no: which if it be true (as I rather wiſh it, then enuie at it) I am content that my homely tranſlation be cancelled: onely this forefront would I haue preſerued, as an old ruinous wall, not for the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, but for the monument of ſome famous inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therein contained; ſo may it ſtand as an heape of ſtones, not onely rebounding a ſhort eccho of <hi>Dubartas</hi> his ſtately voice; but alſo lifting vp the accent in the ſounding praiſes of Maſter <hi>Anthonie Bacon:</hi> and ſubſcribing to the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold prayers for his health and happineſſe, with Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:11253:3"/>
            <head>The Argument.</head>
            <p>THe most Christian Poet in a matter of truth (hauing made his invocation vpon the true God) addreſſeth himſelfe to deſcribe the creation of the world, against the truth whereof bicauſe many opinions of heatheniſh Philoſophers might be oppoſed, he cutteth them downe, as they ſtand in his way. Some dreamed of eternitie, and ſeeing the briers of antiquitie growing over the cleere account of the worlds age, lost themſelues as in a labyrinth, for wane of a directorie thread, to leade to the originall point of the first entrance of the ſame. Others ſtumbled at the beginning thereof, and did ſeeme to hold the circumstance of time, and a former commencement of motion, yet did they denie the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and miſcall the author therof: for they affirmed the world to haue bene patched vp of meats, and ſodainely ſo iumbled together by a caſuall concourſe of the ſame. Our Poet treading the ſteppes of the true Prophets, findeth out an Immortall author and preſeruer, being the ancient of daies, a Father of lights, wich is he that proteſteth of himſelfe, I am before the light was created. And if the Epicure demand what that Author did before he made the world, here is returned the ſame anſwere that Spiridion gaue to the like queſtion in the councel of Neece, <hi>He built a hel for curious queſtioniſts:</hi> &amp; for his company, he was alone and yet not ſolitarie, he had his eſſentiall vertues, his diſtinct perſons all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring in the fulnes of his Godhead which was al in all. Some of the Philoſophers harped vpon this point, but their brains were out of tune, and therfore neuer found out the perfect vnion of thoſe three parts in one. Our Poet expreſſeth the Author God, the inſtrument his word, being the very beginning and alpha of thoſe lines written in the royall parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the heauens, and made legible to all lands and languages. This whole frame and organ of the world tuned by the finger of God and breathed into by his ſpirit, ſerueth as vocall muſicke to conueigh the ſignificant dittie of his power and glorie into euerie ſence. Neither is this world a worke of Imitation ſeconded by any former and externall patern: but of meere nothing was made a rude ſomething at the firſt, by ſixe daies leaſure poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed &amp; extended in ſuch ample compas as we behold, to the intent there might be but one whole entire mound, without whoſe pales there might neither be purleis nor pluralitie of worlds. As it had a beginning, ſo alſo muſt it haue an end, though Plato (of prophane men the moſt deuine) ſhuld affirme the contrary, &amp; al the ſtife conceited ſect of Stoickes ſhuld neceſſarity implead a ſempiternitie: Yet ſuch an end ſhall it haue as euerie venturous. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologer is not able to diſcouer; no, nor any bus the vnſearchable knowledge of the higheſt. God therefore proued the Author and deſtroier, is propoſed as a preſident to vs in that he tooke ſix daies to finiſh that which at a trice he could haue performed. Amongſt his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue labors the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable light is preferred in time, &amp; made the firſt fruit of his creatures: the ſubſtance thereof vncertaine, the beautie and profits therof moſt certaine: what cauſe moued the almightie to diſtinguiſh betweene day and day, light and light, with intercourſe of night and darkenes expreſſed. The angels creation being touched &amp; (according to a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral opinion) attributed to this daies work, the fal of ſom of them, malice of theſe apoſtate relapſes: the perſiſtance and diligent ſeruice of others in the deſence of Gods beloued, and offence of his enimies deſcribed, the Poet takes his farewell for the firſt day.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11253:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>PHillips</hi> faire bloome, ſole eie of <hi>Macedon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hauing diſroabd of all their royaltie</l>
               <l>The loftie towers of thrice-ſackt <hi>Ilion,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was askt by one if he the harpe would ſee,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Paris</hi> vſde amidst his venerie?</l>
               <l>Not <hi>that</hi> quoth he, but rather <hi>THAT</hi> would I:</l>
               <l>Wherewith <hi>Achilles</hi> made ſuch melodie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His minde forſooth and voice accorded then,</l>
               <l>With <hi>THAT</hi> which warbled ſtill the woorthy deedes</l>
               <l>Of heaun-bred ympes, heroick Gentlemen,</l>
               <l>The mortall bloſſoms of immortall ſeedes,</l>
               <l>None ſuch <hi>that other</hi> twangd but worthleſſe weedes.</l>
               <l>As ſighes, ſobs, ſorrowes, and louers languiſhments,</l>
               <l>Or elſe their wiles, ſmiles, ſports, and wanton meriments.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No ſuch like paſſions heere of carpet loue,</l>
               <l>No obiects fit for lewd and lustfull eies:</l>
               <l>Lo heere the <hi>world,</hi> the <hi>earth,</hi> the <hi>heauen</hi> aboue,</l>
               <l>The <hi>elements,</hi> and ſenſe deceiuing skies,</l>
               <l>All made free denizens after Engliſh guiſe:</l>
               <l>You Gentles cast in <hi>Alexanders</hi> mould,</l>
               <l>By choiſe like his, like minde of yours vnfould.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Io. Ho.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11253:4"/>
            <head>THE FIRST DAY OF THE FIRST WEEKE OF du Bartas.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THou, that the courſe of glittring heauen doſt guide</l>
               <l>And checkeſt trucebound <hi>Neptunes</hi> ſurlie waues,<note place="margin">The poets inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation on God.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Shaking the ſteedie earth both far and wide:</l>
               <l>Whoſe word can tame th'Aeolian broad that raues,</l>
               <l>Or cauſe them buſſell from their vented caues;</l>
               <l>Diſchardge my mind of cloudie cares and thought:</l>
               <l>And to thy ſelfe, hale vp my ſprights aloft.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Driue out this ſtatelie drift of me intended,</l>
               <l>And by thy cunning let this verſe be ſquarde,</l>
               <l>So that thy works, by words may be commended:</l>
               <l>Leuie thoſe lines with ſpeciall regard,</l>
               <l>Wherein the worlds rare grow the ſhall be declarde:</l>
               <l>That I may ſing, and latter age may heare,</l>
               <l>How firſt the worlds rude nonage did appeare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great father, graunt that I may couch in meaſure,<note place="margin">The propoſition.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The rareſt points of beautie in this frame,</l>
               <l>And ſpread abroad the chiefe concealed treaſure</l>
               <l>Containing worthie lectures of thy name,</l>
               <l>And ſeruing fit to regiſter thy fame:</l>
               <l>Let me thy ſacred myſteries diſcerne:</l>
               <l>That teaching others them, my ſelfe may learne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The elements from euerlaſting time</l>
               <l>Haue not bene pitcht as we behold them now:</l>
               <l>Nor did the nimble fire ſo euer clime,</l>
               <l>That it kept downe the toſſing aire belowe:<note place="margin">The world was not eternall.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Nor did the aire about the waters bowe:</l>
               <l>Nor water ſhrinking in the earths hollow lap,</l>
               <l>With ſlipprie turnings did the ſame inwrap.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:11253:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>This mightie <hi>Cope,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The world not made by chance.</note> that ſtretcheth wide and ſide,</l>
               <l>Was not rough hewde by fortunes chop or chance:</l>
               <l>Nor in groſſe cluſters of moates vndeſcride,</l>
               <l>Or time ſcrapes vp ruffeled at a glance:</l>
               <l>As vaine <hi>Democritus</hi> dreamd in his trance:</l>
               <l>That ſelfeſame word, whereby the world ſhall fade,</l>
               <l>Was once the word, whereby the world was made.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not made before the meaſuring time was found,</l>
               <l>Without beginning, from eternitie:</l>
               <l>But world and time,<note place="margin">World and time of one ſtanding.</note> at one the ſelfe ſame ſtound,</l>
               <l>As things coequall, tooke formalitie:</l>
               <l>For you (o heauenlie lampes) giue certaintie.</l>
               <l>The ſeaſons, and the times your courſe confirmes</l>
               <l>And cuts the yeares, the months, the daies and termes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Elder then place, then forme of arched skie,</l>
               <l>Elder then time, which wheeles in circle ſpace,</l>
               <l>Sate endles <hi>Ioue</hi> in perfect maieſtie:</l>
               <l>Peizing the whole with more then princelie grace,</l>
               <l>Chearing the parts which all he did imbrace:</l>
               <l>What that was then, I know not how to call:</l>
               <l>Nought els, but God, for God was all in all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One onlie mind, and pure intelligence</l>
               <l>A virgin ſpright, vnſpotted and ſincere:</l>
               <l>Liuing for euer, making no expence</l>
               <l>Of age or time that wrinkles might appeare,</l>
               <l>By nature bright, and alwaies ſhining cleare:</l>
               <l>Fearles and infinite, a lord vnknowen,</l>
               <l>Conuerſing onlie with himſelfe alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:11253:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Wretches, that beat your braines on frantike toies,</l>
               <l>Aske you how mightie Ioue was then imploide?<note place="margin">An anſwere to the Atheiſt, that demandeth what God did, before he made the world.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Making inquirie what were then his ioies,</l>
               <l>When all the world was vncreate and voide?</l>
               <l>His prudent mind (ſaie they) might be annoide,</l>
               <l>Which hauing power to counterpoiſe his will,</l>
               <l>Could ſuffer nothing woorſe than ſitting ſtill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This curious motiue mounts to blaſphemie:</l>
               <l>Another point were fitter to record:</l>
               <l>Before the heauens, and late worlds infancie</l>
               <l>Produced were by his effectuall word,<note place="margin">The Anſwere of Spiridio in the councell of Neece, to the Epicures de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</note>
               </l>
               <l>He built a hell for ſuch as were abhord:</l>
               <l>A hell, for ſuch a proud ambitious rout,</l>
               <l>As Giant-like would caſt their maker out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Doth not a Caruer maſter of his art,</l>
               <l>Draw whilome fancide patternes in his braine,</l>
               <l>Not vſing tooles nor timber in his draught?</l>
               <l>Doth not the Webſter negligent of gaine,</l>
               <l>Lay ſomtimes by both wooffe and warpe in vaine?</l>
               <l>Doth not the Potter leaue his tempered clay,</l>
               <l>Not forging it in veſſels though he may?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſhall the Maſter workman of them all</l>
               <l>Subiect his art vnto ſome lumpiſh ſtuffe,</l>
               <l>As though his skill were meere mechanicall,</l>
               <l>Which in it ſelfe is abſolute enough,</l>
               <l>And by it ſelfe can yeeld ſufficient proofe?</l>
               <l>Neuer was <hi>Scipio</hi> ſolitarie leſſe,</l>
               <l>Than when alone, and had no other gueſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:11253:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Could ſuch a Romane captaine take delight</l>
               <l>Within the cloſet of his humane breſt:</l>
               <l>And ſole ſufficient <hi>Ioue</hi> be thought ſo ſlight,</l>
               <l>That he could not enioie an actiue reſt,</l>
               <l>Amongſt ſuch ioies as cannot be expreſt?</l>
               <l>Might he not liue alone (O heauens, what madnes?)</l>
               <l>As well as men in melancholie ſadnes?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That ancient ſage <hi>Priënaes</hi> great renowne,<note place="margin">Bias.</note>
               </l>
               <l>When he ſhould fleete with bag and baggage thence,</l>
               <l>Bragd he brought all,<note place="margin">Omnia mea mecum porto.</note> yet nothing from the towne,</l>
               <l>His minde was all fraught with intelligence:</l>
               <l>And ſhould rich <hi>Ioue</hi> in his magnificence,</l>
               <l>A Lord and King, and all within himſelfe,</l>
               <l>Deſire to be enricht with worldlie pelfe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>God is the fountaine from whoſe liuely ſpring</l>
               <l>Conduits of grace, and ſtreames of good do flowe,</l>
               <l>All turnes are ſerud by his repleniſhing,</l>
               <l>For worlds of plentie from this fountaine growe,</l>
               <l>He is not ſuppliant to high nor lowe:</l>
               <l>But Ocean-like his fulnes he diſcharges,</l>
               <l>Supplying euerie want with his franke largeſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Before the winds could breath, or waters breed</l>
               <l>The ſpawning fiſh: before the earth was ſtorde</l>
               <l>With Antleere, or enrichde with anie feed,</l>
               <l>Or harueſt crop that fodder might afford:</l>
               <l>Before all this remaind the ſoueraigne Lord,</l>
               <l>Imploid in ſelfe-conceited exerciſe:</l>
               <l>A fit delight for him thats onlie wiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:11253:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>His admirable glorie, puiſſant power,</l>
               <l>Rich bountie, and his ſetled prouidence,</l>
               <l>Were ſacred obiects, preſent eu'rie howre,</l>
               <l>To exerciſe his deepe intelligence,</l>
               <l>And wouldſt thou know his further diligence?</l>
               <l>He did contemplate on this worlds huge frame,</l>
               <l>Viewing a former modell of the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That Father ſolitarie could not be,</l>
               <l>Which had begot before all worlds begun</l>
               <l>An offpring motherles, for companie:</l>
               <l>His word, his wiſdome, and his onelie Son,</l>
               <l>By whoſe conſent all works of waight were done:</l>
               <l>They two both one combinde in puiſſance regall:</l>
               <l>The Father Lord, the Son the Fathers equall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From which two peeres, and powers inuiſible,</l>
               <l>Vnite in mutuall loue and maieſtie,</l>
               <l>Iſſues a third peere indiuiſible:</l>
               <l>And yet to both proportion'd equallie,</l>
               <l>Copartner with the ſacred Deitie;</l>
               <l>Of nature like, although diſtinct in name:</l>
               <l>Of ſundrie gifts, in Godhead all the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My muſe ſtrike ſaile, and launch not in the deepe:</l>
               <l>Beare of aloofe, and hold thy barke at bay:</l>
               <l>From hungrie gulfe of rough Charybdis keepe,</l>
               <l>And ſhun the dreadfull rocks of Capharee,</l>
               <l>Thoſe rocks be wracks and manie mens decay:<note place="margin">The heathen Philoſophersloſt themſelues for want of the true Loadſtar.</note>
               </l>
               <l>For manie ſlipt in maze of curious doubt,</l>
               <l>So whelmde themſelues, they neuer could get out.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:11253:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>A ſafer courſe to cut alongſt the ſhore,</l>
               <l>And beare a point, where landmarks may direct:</l>
               <l>The ſhallow waters beſt can brooke an ore:</l>
               <l>But trifling wherries by the ſeas are checkt:</l>
               <l>In buſie points, let faith thy ſailes erect,</l>
               <l>Gods breathing Spirit be thy happie winde:</l>
               <l>The Bible be a load-ſtar to thy minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What elſe could blinde, our Sages ſecular,</l>
               <l>And make thoſe blinde, ſeduce the vulgar ſort,</l>
               <l>But keeping of a courſe irregular:</l>
               <l>Counter to that the Bible doth exhort:</l>
               <l>Leauing whoſe compaſſe, they muſt needs come ſhort?</l>
               <l>Truthes ſureſt carde, when once they did abandon,</l>
               <l>They loſt themſelues, and others left at randon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A buſie point ſo hard and dangerous,</l>
               <l>As is none ſuch containd in holie writ:</l>
               <l>Apert to thoſe that are not curious,</l>
               <l>Preſuming on diſcourſe of humane wit,</l>
               <l>Or thinke by reaſon to diſcouer it:</l>
               <l>No point more plaine to faithfull minds and holie:</l>
               <l>No point more darke to minds poſſeſt with follie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where am I now? or whither am I puld?</l>
               <l>My clambring mind ſurchargd with percing raies</l>
               <l>Of this celeſtiall maieſtie, is duld:</l>
               <l>Each facultie proceeding thence decaies:</l>
               <l>A ſtatelie threefold brightnes ouerſwaies:</l>
               <l>My voice forgoes hir meditated ſound:</l>
               <l>And in my hart no hart at all is found.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:11253:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>This glorious Trinitie whom I adore</l>
               <l>With bending knee, and lowlie proſtrate hart:</l>
               <l>Whom I beleeue, and trembling ſearch no more,</l>
               <l>Than liuelie faith vouchſafeth to impart:</l>
               <l>This Trinitie by thrice exceeding art,<note place="margin">Three perſons, one God made the world.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Of nothing framde this Mound of huge receipt:</l>
               <l>When all was nothing, but vnmeaſurable great.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Trinitie, ſurpaſſing <hi>Dedalus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This Maſter builder, ſingular for skill,</l>
               <l>Endewd with worlds of wealth, and ſumptuous</l>
               <l>In choiſe of change, yet changeleſſe reſting ſtill,</l>
               <l>Doth boaſt the endleſſe riches of his will:</l>
               <l>Diſplaies his natiue power, and heauenly ſcience;</l>
               <l>And giues to all blaſpheming Momes defiance.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mount who ſo liſt vnto the wheluing ſpheeres,</l>
               <l>As ſcorning of theſe mouldie parts belowe,</l>
               <l>Aboue the heauens let others fetch carreers,</l>
               <l>And ouer bound thoſe balls of ſparkling ſhow:</l>
               <l>Swell they with pride of loftie things they know:</l>
               <l>Let them enioie the counſell of the higheſt:</l>
               <l>And in his courts let them approch the nigheſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And let ſome other lowe conceited wight,</l>
               <l>Take countercourſe, and cowchant to the ground,</l>
               <l>Creepe in theſe muddie obiects next his ſight,</l>
               <l>As wholie in theſe lowlie kennels drownd:</l>
               <l>Searching what force in pettie works is found:</l>
               <l>And finding there ſome notes of Gods owne glorie,</l>
               <l>Eclipſe the ſame, by telling of the ſtorie.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:11253:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Belowe the former, but aboue the laſt,</l>
               <l>I traine my muſe,<note place="margin">Mediocria fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma: medio tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimus ibis.</note> amidſt the midmoſt aire:</l>
               <l>There ſhall ſhe houer, in proportion placde,</l>
               <l>And peizd with equall wings of heedie care:</l>
               <l>Leaſt ſoaring high, hir flight ſhe might impaire,</l>
               <l>Where blazing lamps would ſindge hir winged traine,</l>
               <l>Or buzzing lowe, the dampe might ſlug hir vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I pleaſe my ſelfe, in prying vp and downe,</l>
               <l>And eying of the worlds faire countenance:</l>
               <l>Wherein Gods image makes reflexion,</l>
               <l>As in the mirror of his excellence:</l>
               <l>His Godhead ſet in this worlds purueiance,<note place="margin">The Godhead is ſeen in the viſible things of the world.</note>
               </l>
               <l>By tranſparence doth fill my feeble eies:</l>
               <l>Which may not view his brightnes otherwiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If he that lookes againſt the fierie ſparks</l>
               <l>Of glittring <hi>Phebus,</hi> gets a ſunne-burnd face:</l>
               <l>If he that with a fixed eie ſight marks</l>
               <l>That flaming Globe (although from diſtant place)</l>
               <l>Is purblind, onelie with that fulgent grace;</l>
               <l>Who can ſuſtaine the daunting lookes of him,</l>
               <l>That lightning-like diſperſeth life and lim?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of him, that ſeparate in heauenlie throne,</l>
               <l>Did build this ſtatelie Theater beſide</l>
               <l>For men to ſoiourne, and conuerſe vpon:</l>
               <l>Where liuelie prints of maieſtie abide,</l>
               <l>Though but a glimpſe of his power is deſcride:</l>
               <l>And yet his Godhead grauen in this frame,</l>
               <l>Doth teach our childiſh thoughts to ſpell the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:11253:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Great Father (whom no lumpiſh braines conceiue)</l>
               <l>How doſt thon intimate to humane ſenſe,</l>
               <l>The knowledge of thy ſelfe? and giueſt vs leaue</l>
               <l>To feele thy preſence in this worlds contents,</l>
               <l>And read thy glorie in theſe monuments?</l>
               <l>Our fingers feeling, noſtrils drawing ſauour,</l>
               <l>Our palate taſting, all bewraie thy fauour.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From higheſt throne thou ſendſt a roring noiſe,</l>
               <l>And to inſtruct vs, plaiſt the Orator:</l>
               <l>Heauen ſtarts to vnderſtand thy thundring voice,</l>
               <l>And ſpeakes to vs, as thine Ambaſſador,</l>
               <l>Soothlie, each creature is thine auditor:</l>
               <l>The world a publike ſchoole, where we may learne</l>
               <l>Such proper leſſons as thy praiſe concerne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This frame like to a pullie heaues our ſprights,</l>
               <l>And moues our thoughts to climbe by winding ſtares,</l>
               <l>Aboue the ſtories of thoſe heauenlie lights.<note place="margin">Diuers compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons to ſhew the vſe of the worldly frame to Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The mightie God this world a ſhop prepares,</l>
               <l>To make a publike ſhew of his rich wares.</l>
               <l>This world like to a bridge conducts the ſtranger</l>
               <l>By gulfe of Gods deepe ſecret without danger.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And not vnlike a thin tranſparent clowd</l>
               <l>Yeelds paſſage to the beames of <hi>Phebus</hi> light,</l>
               <l>(Not <hi>Phebus</hi> whom <hi>Latonaes</hi> wombe did ſhrowd,</l>
               <l>Lighting by day, and lurking in the night)</l>
               <l>But ſuch a ſunne as alway ſtaies in ſight:</l>
               <l>In thickeſt darknes ſtill perſiſts to ſhine,</l>
               <l>And neuer ſtowpes beneath Orizons line.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:11253:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Heere as in ſemi-circled Theater,</l>
               <l>Loue, Iuſtice, Righteouſnes and Maieſtie,</l>
               <l>Preſent themſelues: which expert actors are,</l>
               <l>Their parts diſcharging ſo ingeniouſly,</l>
               <l>That humane ſenſe is rapt aboue the skie.</l>
               <l>This world a booke in folio, doth proclame</l>
               <l>With letters capitall, the Authors name:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Each kind, a page, each ſundrie ſhape a line;</l>
               <l>Each creature, is a character to teach:</l>
               <l>Each worke, a vowell, ſounding diſcipline:</l>
               <l>And all the world doth conſonantly preach:</l>
               <l>But we are trewants, which from maſters reach,</l>
               <l>On toies and gawds do ſet their wanton harts,</l>
               <l>Reſpecting them more than regarding arts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our eies be wandring on the babiſh gaies,</l>
               <l>And flowres that fill the waſt comportenance:</l>
               <l>On backſide of the booke we ſpend our daies,</l>
               <l>Not vſing natures text, a furtherance</l>
               <l>To helpe inſtruct our blindfold ignorance:</l>
               <l>Thence might we learne that God is chiefeſt cauſe,</l>
               <l>Supporting cities peace with wholſome lawes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What do we trauell in the multitude</l>
               <l>Of languages? and labour to explaine</l>
               <l>The ſenſe, which Turkiſh characters include?</l>
               <l>Or Aegypts ſacred figures do containe?</l>
               <l>What thoſe ſmall pricks in th'Ebrew language meane?</l>
               <l>To know the notes and accents of the Greeke,</l>
               <l>Theſe things ſo ſlight, what neede we greatly ſeeke?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:11253:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>The Scythian and the wildt Tartarian,</l>
               <l>The ſeuen yeeres wit, not growne yet to be wiſe,</l>
               <l>And thoſe that haue the Pole meridian,</l>
               <l>By natures light can ſcand theſe myſteries,</l>
               <l>Saunce further inſight, than by carnall eies:</l>
               <l>But he that is illuminate by faith,</l>
               <l>Moues from this mould, and mounts a greater haith.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He vawts aboue the criſtall firmament,</l>
               <l>And vnderneath his feet, beholds the ſtirre</l>
               <l>Of ſpheeres conuerted by Gods regiment:</l>
               <l>Whence reading his celeſtiall kalender,</l>
               <l>He proues to be an arch-Aſtronomer.</l>
               <l>Aided with faith, I long to be diſcerning</l>
               <l>The ſacred text of Gods inſpired learning.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My pleaſure is to couch in ſtatelie verſe</l>
               <l>The worlds firſt birth and tender nurſerie,</l>
               <l>The eaning, and the weaning I reherſe,</l>
               <l>The infant nonage, and minoritie,</l>
               <l>And how it grew to perfect dignitie.</l>
               <l>I will vnfold the boſome of this frame,</l>
               <l>That all may read Gods eſſence in the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The founder of this ouerſpreading tent,</l>
               <l>Tooke no fantaſticke copie for his guide,</l>
               <l>No borrowed ſhadow for his preſident,</l>
               <l>Nor melancholie did he long abide,<note place="margin">God tooke no view of any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall patterne to make the world after.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Inuenting how the parts might be applide:</l>
               <l>There was no world, before this world, erected:</l>
               <l>No former plot nor patterne he reſpected.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:11253:10"/>
            <lg>
               <l>An earthly builder, toſſing in his braynes,</l>
               <l>How beſt to raiſe a pallace for a king:</l>
               <l>Firſt craueth reſpite, counſell, taketh paynes</l>
               <l>To make ſuruey of many a ſuch like thing,</l>
               <l>Before he ſets his hand to faſhioning,</l>
               <l>That after diuers pallaces beheld,</l>
               <l>Himſelfe at laſt, might exquiſitely build.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where any queint conueiance is compriſde,</l>
               <l>He markes the point, the workmanſhip, and grace:</l>
               <l>Heere he commends the forefront, well deuiſd,</l>
               <l>Elſe-where, ſome pillar raiſd on comely baſe,</l>
               <l>Or ſtares well mounted honoring the place:</l>
               <l>Surueying much, he notes a thouſand things,</l>
               <l>And in his worke the grace of all he brings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No ſuch examples of Ichnographie</l>
               <l>Had euerlaſting <hi>Ioue</hi> to imitate,</l>
               <l>That he might forge a ſecond world thereby,</l>
               <l>And frame a worke, for worlds to woonder at:</l>
               <l>He neuer ſweat, nor beat his braynes for that,</l>
               <l>But caſt the world with eaſe into a ſquare:</l>
               <l>Quartered with earth, and water, fire, and aire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Euen as the Sunne (earths faireſt husbandman)</l>
               <l>Annexed to the wheeling firmament,</l>
               <l>Deſcendeth not from his pauilion;</l>
               <l>But ſends from thence his fruitfull increment,</l>
               <l>Cheering the loue-ſicke earth with meriment:</l>
               <l>Although he liſt not come, yet doth he ſend</l>
               <l>Garlands of plentie to his diſtant frend.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:11253:10"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Gods pleaſure, and performance, will, and deed,</l>
               <l>Conceit, and act, are of one equall age:</l>
               <l>Purpoſe and practiſe, word and worke, proceed,</l>
               <l>And march alike, with perfect aequipage,</l>
               <l>As ofsprings of one heauenly parentage:</l>
               <l>All keepe their courſe inioynd, on God attendant:</l>
               <l>He was their maker, and is their defendant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But yet the matter of this comely frame</l>
               <l>Was not foorthwith ſo curious to behold:</l>
               <l>Nor ſo polite, as now we ſee the ſame,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Ioue</hi> had caſt it in a fairer mold:</l>
               <l>For as a ſhipwright (not to be comptrold)</l>
               <l>When he ſhould build a barke to checke the ſeas,</l>
               <l>By leaſure lookes what kinds of ſtuffe he pleaſe:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Firſt trees for tymber; iron, pytch for ſtrength:</l>
               <l>Then he prouides his cables and his cord:</l>
               <l>Which all he layes on heapes: vntill at length,</l>
               <l>He ſingles out a ſayle-yard from the hord:</l>
               <l>The beake, and ſterne he makes of ſome choyſe bord:</l>
               <l>The talleſt firre he marketh for his maſt:</l>
               <l>Vntill by art, ech part is fitly plac'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So God before this world was poliſhed,</l>
               <l>Produc'd his pregnant and immortall word;</l>
               <l>And then collecting all the parts vntride,</l>
               <l>He mendgd them all, in one confuſed hord:</l>
               <l>But where the Shipwright to his hands is ſtord;</l>
               <l>God was the author both of forme and ſtuffe,</l>
               <l>Not borrowing ought, for he had all enough.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:11253:11"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Baſe was the worlds firſt viſage, and vncowth,</l>
               <l>An Auerne dungeon, toſt with heedles quoyle:</l>
               <l>A rifraffe medley;<note place="margin">The world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out forme, faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, place, at the firſt.</note> and a gulphall mouth,</l>
               <l>A ſluggiſh heape of Elements at ſoyle,</l>
               <l>Amongſt themſelues pell mell all one the ſpoyle:</l>
               <l>Cold nipt the heat, ſquare things and round did iar:</l>
               <l>The hard and rough, with ſoft and ſmooth, made war.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Moiſture and drouth, high mounting things &amp; humble,</l>
               <l>At hurlie-burlie skattered on a ranke,</l>
               <l>In ciuill ſtrife vnciuillie did tumble:</l>
               <l>The fire, and aire, plaid many a lawles pranke:</l>
               <l>The water skornd to keepe within a banke:</l>
               <l>Nor earth, nor aire, retained bound or border:</l>
               <l>But all things were, vnperfect, out of order.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Somtime the water kept ſuch heaue and ſhoue,</l>
               <l>That it incrochde vpon the victorie:</l>
               <l>The aire ſomtimes by ſtrugling did remoue</l>
               <l>The waters force, and got the maſterie:</l>
               <l>Somtime the earth did cruſh the other three:</l>
               <l>Eftſoones the fire aboue them all did skip,</l>
               <l>When topſie turuie downe the reſt did ſlip.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That high Lord Marſhall darting thunderſhot,</l>
               <l>As yet had not his offices diſpoſd:</l>
               <l>The ſhapeles skie had not one glyſtering ſpot;</l>
               <l>Nor any Planetarie ſigne that gloſd:</l>
               <l>The earth had not hir motley weeds impoſd:</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Neptune</hi> had his watriſh kingdome ſtorde:</l>
               <l>Nor any foule amidſt the welkin ſoarde.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:11253:11"/>
            <lg>
               <l>All things lay weltring in a ſlothfull ſhade:</l>
               <l>No quickning ſpright did animate the lumpe:<note place="margin">Genoſ. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The blended fire, no fierie geſture had:</l>
               <l>The earth, no earth, the aire could make no thumpe:</l>
               <l>Theſe firſt borne creatures ſtucke as in a dumpe:</l>
               <l>No ſetled courſe, degrees or bounds ordained,</l>
               <l>By which this reuell rout might be reſtrained.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If fire were then; twas not poſſeſt with heat:</l>
               <l>If aire; it did not thorough ſhine with light:</l>
               <l>If water; yet the moyſture was not great:</l>
               <l>If earth; it tottering daunc'd for lacke of weight:</l>
               <l>Do but imagine ſuch an auckwoorth ſight,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Tellus</hi> bald and barren were preſented,</l>
               <l>Not firme, nor plaine, nor yet with dales indented.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Suppoſe the heauens diſrobde of all their pride:</l>
               <l>Thoſe eies pockt out, and lights extinguiſhed,</l>
               <l>Debard of motion and all forme beſide,</l>
               <l>And thinke thou ſeeſt the firſt world pictured,</l>
               <l>Whoſe portraiture can not be vttered,</l>
               <l>What then was not, I better can declare,</l>
               <l>Then what that was, which was of old time theare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>World was it not, but hope of world to come,</l>
               <l>A lumpe that askt ſixe daies the finiſhing,</l>
               <l>A likelihood ſuch as in mothers wombe</l>
               <l>The fruite giues firſt, when firſt it ginnes to ſpring,<note place="margin">Embrye.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Which growes ſo long till it be liuely thing:</l>
               <l>Firſt face, then eies, then chin, and noſtrils parting,</l>
               <l>Then hands diſtinct, and fingers thereto ſorting.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:11253:12"/>
            <lg>
               <l>This pettie world, thus at the length increaſd,</l>
               <l>Obtaineth vigour for his enterpriſe:</l>
               <l>And out of priſon ſtriues to be releaſd,</l>
               <l>Getting a larger proſpect for his eies:</l>
               <l>Yet in this maſſe a ſecret vertue lies,</l>
               <l>Which hath by nature force to forme and giue</l>
               <l>A vitall act, whereby the fleſh may liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That vaſter heape had no ſelfe-quickning ſpright,</l>
               <l>No naturall actiuitie to grow:</l>
               <l>And therefore had in dulnes moultred quight,</l>
               <l>But that Gods ſacred word began to flow,</l>
               <l>And with his influence inſpird it ſo,</l>
               <l>That it became a vegetable brood,</l>
               <l>And was partaker of ſuch liuelihoode.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A darkſome horror, ſuch as Aegypt felt,</l>
               <l>With blindfold eies, and harts aſtoniſhment:</l>
               <l>Blacknes, like that where the Cimmerians dwelt,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Sibb</hi> vnto <hi>Mephitis</hi> helliſh ſent,</l>
               <l>Belchd from the puddle Styx, Gods puniſhment:</l>
               <l>Or if ſome darknes be more palpable,</l>
               <l>Of that, and all was <hi>Chaos</hi> capable.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Confuſed reuell and diſorder raigning,</l>
               <l>This waxing world was like to ruinate:</l>
               <l>Had not Gods powre their mutines reſtraining,</l>
               <l>Diſperſt it ſelfe into that rude eſtate,</l>
               <l>And qualified the rage of their debate,<note place="margin">The ſpirit moued vpon the water. Geneſ. 1.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Had not his vertue like to ſodder cloſd</l>
               <l>The chops and rents of matter indiſpoſd,</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:11253:12"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Had it not bound as with a maſtique glue,</l>
               <l>The heauens, earth, aire, and vagrant Ocean:</l>
               <l>And fixed liſtes to keepe apart that crue,</l>
               <l>Their natures in the cradell euery one</l>
               <l>Had bin extinct with ſelfe commotion:</l>
               <l>But Gods great puiſſance ſhed into this hord,</l>
               <l>Aſſwagd the ſtriffe: and bred a ſweete accord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As ſome braue wit reſolu'd to conſecrate</l>
               <l>A worke of waight vnto the Muſes ſhryne:</l>
               <l>At home, abroad, at bed, bourd, earely, late,</l>
               <l>Rippes his diſcourſe and ponders euery lyne,</l>
               <l>Hovring amongſt his books of diſcipline:</l>
               <l>So Gods great ſpright which was the onely mouer,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 1.2.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Vpon the waters ſuperfice did houer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Euen as the brooding bird that ſits at once,</l>
               <l>To hatch hir egges, and huckle vp hir yonge,</l>
               <l>Till natiue and adoptiue egges breed bones,</l>
               <l>And all hir flocke is fledge and liuely ſprong:</l>
               <l>So Gods owne ſpirit ſate, though not ſo long,</l>
               <l>And farre and neere did ſpread his ripning wings</l>
               <l>Till he had perfected theſe callowe things.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Out of the ſuds, where monſterlike they lay,</l>
               <l>He did extract them: altering their hue:</l>
               <l>Extending ſuch an vniuerſall baye,</l>
               <l>As ouerreachd this compaſſe which we viewe;</l>
               <l>And was compleat with all the reſidue:</l>
               <l>All was but one thing, neither markd, nor bounded:</l>
               <l>Nothing remaind that was not there impounded.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:11253:13"/>
            <lg>
               <l>If that Archduke from God in Horeb taught,</l>
               <l>Had not this certaine teſtimonie yeelded,</l>
               <l>How firſt the vniuerſall world was wrought,</l>
               <l>And in ſixe daies this ſtately frame ſo builded,</l>
               <l>By that ſame God which all things wrought &amp; weilded:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Leucippus</hi> might by arguments perſwade,<note place="margin">A pluralitie of worlds confuted.</note>
               </l>
               <l>That ſome great multitude of worlds were made.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nature (no niggard of hir workmanſhip)</l>
               <l>If ſhe had coinde manie worlds in number,</l>
               <l>The heauie earth would ruſh, the water drip,</l>
               <l>And make one neighbour world anothers cumber:</l>
               <l>So all might fall into their wonted ſlumber:</l>
               <l>Or leaſt the one the others courſe ſhould hinder,</l>
               <l>Some emptie ſpace muſt keepe the frames aſunder.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now the engine was ſo firmely iointed,</l>
               <l>So cloſe compact without one creuiſe void,</l>
               <l>With furniſht complements ſo well appointed,</l>
               <l>That nothing was by vacant chinks annoid.</l>
               <l>We ſee, how cloſe ſtopt wine cannot auoid,</l>
               <l>Nor iſſue currantly from out the terſe,</l>
               <l>Except a vent to take in aire we perſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We ſee the puffing bellowes cannot heaue,</l>
               <l>If at the noſe they ſnuffe not vp the wind:</l>
               <l>Bungd veſſels cannot anie froſt receiue,</l>
               <l>Not cloſed waterpots an iſſue find.</l>
               <l>Forc'd liquor drawne in pipes againſt the kind,</l>
               <l>Doth mount aloft as though it were no water,</l>
               <l>So great a foe is emptines to nature.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:11253:13"/>
            <lg>
               <l>God, onlie great, beyonde all quantitie,<note place="margin">God, onlie infinite the worlde hath his limited mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of time and place.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Framed the courſe of nature mutable:</l>
               <l>From change exempting his diuinitie,</l>
               <l>Making time meaſure althings moueable:</l>
               <l>For heauens themſelues are not vnmeaſurable:</l>
               <l>Time meets the circuit of the firmament,</l>
               <l>And rules the motions with his regiment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The world, is not immortall, though ſo vaſt,</l>
               <l>But ſubiect vnto rauenouſe decay:</l>
               <l>The parts do languiſh, and the members waſt:</l>
               <l>And, like the parts, the whole muſt weare away:</l>
               <l>To euery thing prefixed is a day:</l>
               <l>The daie calles death, ſtill gaping to deuoure:</l>
               <l>And natures wheele is turned euery houre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now go vaine Greece, and weaue heauens curtaincloth</l>
               <l>Of braine ſpun threads, ſuch as thy quinteſſence:<note place="margin">The quinteſſence of Ariſtotle.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Fill all the world with fancies windie froth,</l>
               <l>Painting fond fables with faire eloquence:</l>
               <l>Diſpute, according thine intelligence,</l>
               <l>And ſay; the courſe of heauen was near begone:</l>
               <l>Nor, euer in thy iudgement ſhall haue done.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Stand on the vrgent lawes of deſtinier</l>
               <l>And locke vp all within their hard precinct,<note place="margin">The ſtoicall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie.</note>
               </l>
               <l>As bound to tocke of ſtarke neceſſitie:</l>
               <l>Yet not the ſtars ſo ſlauiſhly are link'd,</l>
               <l>But monthly they receaue a freſh inſtinct,</l>
               <l>Such fables are not able to defend,</l>
               <l>The worldly frame from ruine in the end.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:11253:14"/>
            <lg>
               <l>The day ſhall come,<note place="margin">A deſcription of the worlds end.</note> when rocks rent from the quarrie,</l>
               <l>And trembling tops of loftie hils ſhall ruſh:</l>
               <l>When heauens ſhall cracke, and lowly vales miſcarrie,</l>
               <l>Stuft vp with ſheards, and ſuffring many a bruſh</l>
               <l>Of huge great heapes, that cannot chuſe but cruſh:</l>
               <l>The rubbiſh of the ruinated heauen,</l>
               <l>Shall make the mountaines and the valleies euen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Gape ſhall the chanels, void of water ſtreames,</l>
               <l>Or hauing moyſture, all imbrew'de with bloud,</l>
               <l>Shall hyſſe with heate of ſcorching fierie beames:</l>
               <l>The ſea ſhall vomite lightnings as a floud,</l>
               <l>And blazing flame ſhall fome vp like the ſud:</l>
               <l>The Whales halfe roaſted on the bancke ſhall rore:</l>
               <l>And gaſping lie vpon the new found ſhore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The foggie clouds ſhall muffle vp the day:</l>
               <l>The cheerefull Sunne ſhall mourne in fearefull maske:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Neptunes</hi> tayle ſhall ſweepe the ſtarres away,</l>
               <l>Both Sun and Moone ſhall ſhun their woonted taske,</l>
               <l>In fogs ſhall one, in bloud the other baske.</l>
               <l>The darting ſtars ſhall cleaue the earth aſunder,</l>
               <l>And forth ſhal march fear, death, dark ſtorms &amp; thunder</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoſe marſhald in their quarters, ſhall attend</l>
               <l>The wrathfull vengeance of their Lord approching:</l>
               <l>All wicked harts ſhall fayle to ſee that end,</l>
               <l>And heare the Iudge their own lewd deeds reproching,</l>
               <l>With thouſand torments on them ſtill incroching:</l>
               <l>Nought ſhall the world be but a flaming ball,</l>
               <l>Light fire (like water once) ſurrounding all.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:11253:14"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas, what meanes the misbeleeuing pen</l>
               <l>Of ſottiſh wizards, ſcribling Almanakes;</l>
               <l>To marke the yeare, the month, or ſeaſon when</l>
               <l>This fleeting world, full point and period makes:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Saturnes</hi> port a <hi>Superſedeas</hi> takes?</l>
               <l>As though ſome croſſe aſpect of wandring ſtarres</l>
               <l>Should cruſh the world by furie of their iarres.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I tremble to relate: and thorough hart and ioints</l>
               <l>A chill cold horror ſhoots:<note place="margin">Againſt the baſer ſort of aſtrologers which dare ſet forth their predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the time whem doomes day ſhall come.</note> when I do ponder</l>
               <l>How ſome baſe figure-flingers broch theſe points,</l>
               <l>Foreſtalling God the onely worlds confounder:</l>
               <l>To mooue the people to a faithles wonder.</l>
               <l>For their coniectures taken by their theame,</l>
               <l>Iudicials and all, are but a dreame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet grope they at Gods ſealed cloſſet dore,</l>
               <l>And would be prying at thoſe myſteries,</l>
               <l>Which he hath treaſured vp for ſecret ſtore:</l>
               <l>Keeping the diall of all deſtinies</l>
               <l>Vnto himſelfe, that knowes all ſecrecies:</l>
               <l>That Kalender he ſhuts vp in his hand,</l>
               <l>Wherein Doomes-day with letters red doth ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That day, whereof no man can read the date,</l>
               <l>Shall ſwiftly ſtrike the rowt of men ſecure:</l>
               <l>And ſtriking warne, when warning is too late:</l>
               <l>For times delay no longer may endure.</l>
               <l>Then comes thy Sonne (O Father eſſence pure,)</l>
               <l>Thy glorious Sonne with maieſtie ſhall come,<note place="margin">The ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt.</note>
               </l>
               <l>In ſhape of man, once formed in the wombe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:11253:15"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Immortall God, that glorious Sonne of thine,</l>
               <l>In flaming fire triumphant ſhall deſcend:</l>
               <l>About whoſe throne ſhall troupes of Angels ſhine,</l>
               <l>And thouſand thouſand holie ſaints attend,</l>
               <l>Ioious to ſee that long deſired end.</l>
               <l>His chariot wheeles ſhall skud like lightning flame:</l>
               <l>Iuſtice and mercie haling on the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then, ſuch as ſleepe in bowels of the graue,</l>
               <l>Oppreſt with duſt, or weight of marble toombes:</l>
               <l>Such as the ſea hath ſwallowd in hir caue:</l>
               <l>Such as by fire receiud their former doomes,</l>
               <l>Or paunch of beaſts haue had for buriall roomes:</l>
               <l>All ſhall ſtand vp repaird with manlike ſhape,</l>
               <l>No one, ſo great or ſmall, that ſhall eſcape.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All muſt appeere, appeering muſt attend</l>
               <l>In their owne perſons, till the Iudge proceed,</l>
               <l>Awarding life or death to be their end:</l>
               <l>Of mercie ſome, of iuſtice other ſpeed:</l>
               <l>Too ſome is weale, to others wo decreed:</l>
               <l>Some to the loweſt pit ſhall be debaſed,</l>
               <l>And others with the higheſt ſhall be graced.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O thou (whom once th'Italian Preſident</l>
               <l>Pronouncing wicked ſentence terrifide)</l>
               <l>Grant me,<note place="margin">Pilate.</note> that when thy trumpet ſhall be ſent</l>
               <l>To ſound a ſommons vpon eurie ſide,</l>
               <l>Eaſt, weſt, north, ſouth, where anie men abide:</l>
               <l>Rowzing the world with ſudden change of ſtate,</l>
               <l>I may haue thee, my iudge and Aduocate.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:11253:15"/>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſage and powerfull prouidence of <hi>Ioue</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Brought out this world as ſhe beare foles hir yoong:<note place="margin">The creation of the worlds mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from nothing.</note>
               </l>
               <l>A lumpiſh gobbet, firſt vnapt to moue,</l>
               <l>Till it be lickt, and trickt vp with the toong:</l>
               <l>She ſpares no paines, till all the lims be ſproong:</l>
               <l>She ſmoothes it vp, with mouth, and mothers moiſture,</l>
               <l>Till ſhe diſcloſe the ſhape, hid in the cloiſture.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By licking ſhe expreſſeth eurie lim:</l>
               <l>She formes the head, and faſhions out the feet,</l>
               <l>Indents the pawes, and makes the viſage grim,</l>
               <l>Rough caſts the ſhag hair'd ſhoulders: as is meet,</l>
               <l>In euerie part, ſhe ſhewes hir ſelfe diſcreet:</l>
               <l>Diſcreet and diligent, till ſhe haue done,</l>
               <l>And brought hir whelpe to iuſt perfection.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For when Gods wiſdome, by his pregnant voice</l>
               <l>Powrd out a maſſe of heate, cold, moiſt and drie:</l>
               <l>In proceſſe, he gan make exacter choice,</l>
               <l>And ſeparate the low lie things from high:</l>
               <l>Conſorting like with like, diſlike laid by:</l>
               <l>Fire ioind with fire, things heauie found like matter:</l>
               <l>Cold drew to cold, and liquid things to water.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The queinteſt forme, that beſt beſeemes each part,</l>
               <l>Is vnto each particular aſſignd:</l>
               <l>And in ſixe daies God ſhewd his matchleſſe art,</l>
               <l>Forming this world conformall to his mind:</l>
               <l>Not, but he could haue all theſe things refind,</l>
               <l>And perfected in leſſe than times leaſt tittle,</l>
               <l>Vnlike to man thats long about a little.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:11253:16"/>
            <lg>
               <l>The heauens he could haue ſpangled with their lamps:</l>
               <l>And ſtorde the airie cage, with winged breed:</l>
               <l>The foreſt where the ſauadge Beuie rampes,</l>
               <l>He could haue furniſht foorth with for a need:</l>
               <l>And fild the ſeas with fiſhes in like ſpeed:</l>
               <l>But yet it was his vncomptrouled pleaſure;<note place="margin">Why God would take ſixe daies for his creation.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To worke them out in ſixe whole daies at leaſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So many daies, ſuch leaſure, and ſuch art,</l>
               <l>Beſtowd in preparation of a ſeat</l>
               <l>For man vnformed, ſeemeth to impart,</l>
               <l>That doubtles his good will is woonderous great</l>
               <l>To thoſe, for whom he made this goodly ſeat:</l>
               <l>To whom by promiſe, he firſt ſeald a warrant</l>
               <l>Of thouſand fauours afterward apparant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He gaue an imitable preſident,</l>
               <l>That we ſhould not, in ouer eager haſte</l>
               <l>Poſt in our toyle, till breath and ſtrength be ſpent:</l>
               <l>Nor raſhlie ruffle vp our works to waſte,</l>
               <l>But make good ſpeed, yet hurrie not too faſte,</l>
               <l>Aduiſement alwaies brings an act to proofe:<note place="margin">Sat cito, ſi ſat bene. Foſtina lente:</note>
               </l>
               <l>And things well done are all done ſoone enough.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Father of wiſdome, father of the light;</l>
               <l>What firſt might be extracted from that traunce,</l>
               <l>Where all things lay confuſde without delight</l>
               <l>More woorthie then the lights faire countenaunce?</l>
               <l>Whoſe abſence were faire beauties hinderaunce:<note place="margin">Light the firſt fruite of Gods creatures.</note>
               </l>
               <l>For without light <hi>Timanthes</hi> had in vaine</l>
               <l>To carue his antique <hi>Cyclops</hi> tooke ſuch paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:11253:16"/>
            <lg>
               <l>In vaine <hi>Parrhaſius</hi> had ſhapt his peece:</l>
               <l>And Zeuxis drawne his queint <hi>Penelope:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apelles</hi> had expreſt the floure of Greece</l>
               <l>Dame <hi>Venus,</hi> to no purpoſe, if ſo be</l>
               <l>The Sunne had not affoorded light to ſee:</l>
               <l>In vaine thoſe maſters artificiall,</l>
               <l>Had raiſd their woonders ſupernaturall:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dianes</hi> temple: and that moniment</l>
               <l>Of loue and death <hi>Mauſolus</hi> tombe much famed:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Pharos</hi> beacon; works of woonderment,</l>
               <l>By three great maſters exquiſitely framed:</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Soſtrat, Scopas, Cteſiphon</hi> are named:</l>
               <l>In vaine thoſe maruailes all had been erected:</l>
               <l>If by the light, they had not been detected.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What more hath euerie artſman in requeſt,</l>
               <l>When he doth frame an exquiſite deuiſe;</l>
               <l>Then that the worlds faire eie which lights the reſt,</l>
               <l>Should alſo glaunce vpon his worke of price?</l>
               <l>For that intent, his windowe open lies:</l>
               <l>He doth admit the ſunne-light for a witnes,</l>
               <l>That he obſerues proportion, art and fitnes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Either Gods actiue ſpirit houering,</l>
               <l>Vpon the boyling confluence of water,</l>
               <l>Which wrapt the <hi>Chaos</hi> as a couering,</l>
               <l>Strooke out light fire by ſecret force of nature,<note place="margin">diuerſe opinions touching the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and creation of the light.</note>
               </l>
               <l>As when contrarie winds begun to clatter,</l>
               <l>In Sommer nights, and clap two clouds together:</l>
               <l>From hence proceed, bright flames &amp; lightning wether.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:11253:17"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Or God by parts diſpoſing of the maſſe,</l>
               <l>Fetchd brightnes from the fierie element:</l>
               <l>Or heauens cleare curtaine that extended was,</l>
               <l>In twiſe ſixe houres vpon that litterment,</l>
               <l>Againe by God was darkned: to th'intent,</l>
               <l>That ech Horizon ſhould by turnes haue light:</l>
               <l>And each againe an intercourſe of night:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or whether God produc'd a chriſtall lampe,</l>
               <l>In countenance vnlike vnto the Sunne,</l>
               <l>And with another light clear'd vp the dampe,</l>
               <l>While ſomtimes vp and ſomtimes downe it runne,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Titan</hi> brandiſhing his ſtation;</l>
               <l>Let there be light (ſaid God,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 1.3.</note>) no ſooner ſpoken,</l>
               <l>But Light began to ſhew a glorious token.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The gliſtring raies, acknowledging their dutie,</l>
               <l>Do ſhed themſelues on nature, being glad,</l>
               <l>To feele the cheering ſparks of lights faire beautie:</l>
               <l>Who skornes the ſhade wherewith ſhe erſt was clad,</l>
               <l>And loaths to be, or ſuffer others ſad.</l>
               <l>Cleere lampe, God giue thee many goodly morrowes,</l>
               <l>That chaſeſt night, and putſt to flight all ſorrowes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou worlds great candell: &amp; thou truths right parent,</l>
               <l>Terrour of theeues, and perfect looking glaſſe</l>
               <l>Of Gods good creatures, made by thee apparent:</l>
               <l>Firſt fruit of God beſpread vpon the maſſe;</l>
               <l>How doth thy beautie and thy grace ſurpaſſe?</l>
               <l>Gods cheerefull eie: which all the world ſuruaies,</l>
               <l>Why ſhould not modeſt men chaunt out thy praiſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:11253:17"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And yet becauſe all pleaſures do diſpleaſe,</l>
               <l>That haue no blancke nor intercourſe betweene:<note place="margin">Why God ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the night to ſucceed the day.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And they beſt know the benefit of eaſe,</l>
               <l>Which long in garboyles of the wars haue beene:</l>
               <l>For contraries comparde are better ſeene,</l>
               <l>The ſyluer Swan, that ſhines vpon Cayſter,</l>
               <l>Matchd with the ſwarthy crow, doth much more gliſter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore the worlds renowned Architect</l>
               <l>Ordaind the night to preaſe vpon the day:<note place="margin">The commodities of the night.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The day againe, nights error to detect,</l>
               <l>The night daies eager ſchorches to allay:</l>
               <l>And th'aire with ſhowring vapors to aray:</l>
               <l>The night makes mellow ſeeds ſprout in the furrowes,</l>
               <l>Surceaſeth toyle: and breakes off daily ſorrowes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The night which couers all, with wings of pyteh,</l>
               <l>Doth huſh the world, and lull it in a ſleepe:</l>
               <l>Infuſing ſilence, that no creatures quitch:</l>
               <l>But dronke with influence of ſlumber deepe,</l>
               <l>Both man and beaſt, do lay their limmes in ſleepe.</l>
               <l>The nights refreſh their wearie bones with eaſe,</l>
               <l>And make amends for the'anguiſh of the daies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sweete night, without thee, and thy welcome preſence,</l>
               <l>Life were a hell, where (furie like) ſad griefe,</l>
               <l>Reuenge, paine, auarice would daſh all pleaſance,</l>
               <l>And thouſand deaths, before deaths laſt repreefe,</l>
               <l>Would torture minde and bodie ſaunce releefe:</l>
               <l>Sweete night, thou coulorſt euerie perſonage</l>
               <l>In ſuits alike, that plaies on worldly ſtage.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:11253:18"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou blendeſt ſtates, and all diſtinction,</l>
               <l>Which day light varies in a ſundrie guiſe:</l>
               <l>Thou equalleſt the king and cullion,</l>
               <l>The rich, and poore, the ſimple, and the wiſe,</l>
               <l>The iudge, and him that in dungeon lies:</l>
               <l>Maſter and ſlaue: foule maukyn and faire may:</l>
               <l>Daies candle out, the night maks all things gray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that for ſome vngratious deed, remaines</l>
               <l>A creature damnd to delue in golden mines:</l>
               <l>And in thoſe traps of auarice, takes paines:</l>
               <l>He that all ſmokie at the fornace pines,</l>
               <l>Whiles he the ſulphur of mans hart refines:</l>
               <l>Though all daie long, his helliſh toile doth laſt:</l>
               <l>Yet at the night, he takes his due repaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that alongſt the riuer tugs his boat,</l>
               <l>With pugs and oares againſt the ſtubborne tide:</l>
               <l>And dropping ripe, doth ſtraine his rugged throat,</l>
               <l>That voice and ſtrength may both his litour guide;</l>
               <l>At night vnto his pallate ſteps aſide.</l>
               <l>He that the ſpring proud medowes frizled haire</l>
               <l>Doth barbe with ſithe: at night goes to his lare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Onlie you children of the bookiſh maids,</l>
               <l>While all the world is ouercaſt with night,</l>
               <l>Trace out a path, by your celeſtiall trades,</l>
               <l>Whereby into the heauens you take your flight,</l>
               <l>And with your muſe raiſe others to delight.</l>
               <l>But the eu'ning chime hath rong daies lateſt houre,</l>
               <l>The light ſhut in, the daies begins to loure:</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:11253:18"/>
            <lg>
               <l>The night, vnbender of my head ſtrong ſtuddie,</l>
               <l>Approcheth near: but new ſupplie of paines,</l>
               <l>Appeares as ſoone, as morning peares out ruddie:</l>
               <l>And ſtill more worke dares on my wearie braines:</l>
               <l>For now behold in numerable traines,</l>
               <l>And ſquadrons of celeſtiall ſouldiers muſter:</l>
               <l>Dazling mine eies with their bright orient cluſter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You angels (Gods attentiue purſeuaunts)</l>
               <l>Be it, you are coequall to the light,<note place="margin">A diſcourſe of the Angels creation, which are thought vnder the name of light to haue bene cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated: without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining vpon ſo difficult a point.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Which drowns the name of your ſignificance:</l>
               <l>Or then firſt tooke your ſeruiceable flight,</l>
               <l>When heauen was ſpangled with thoſe aglets bright:</l>
               <l>Or, be you ancients to each other creature:</l>
               <l>Surpaſſing them in eſſence, time and feature:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Me liſteth not to argue <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>con;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or vndertake with ſtubborne conference,</l>
               <l>To dwell in this or that opinion:</l>
               <l>In points vncertaine obſtinate defence</l>
               <l>I do diſlike, and iangling arguments:</l>
               <l>Blind ſophiſtrie is bold and full of taunts:</l>
               <l>But my ſure card is humble ignorance.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet this I know, and therefore make no doubt,</l>
               <l>You actiue ſpirits, once were all created</l>
               <l>Immortall innocent, and faire throughout:</l>
               <l>And with great choiſe of heauenlie vertues fraghted,</l>
               <l>That with no creatures els, you could be mated:</l>
               <l>To Gods pure eſſence you approch the nigheſt:</l>
               <l>Alone inferior vnto the higheſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:11253:19"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But as deſertles wights, whom countenance</l>
               <l>And princes fauor, deigneth to exalt;</l>
               <l>Mounted on honors backe, begin to praunce,</l>
               <l>And gainſt their founder make vniuſt aſſault,</l>
               <l>Till downe againe, they ſlip for their proud fault:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo ſome rout of theſe created ſpirits,</l>
               <l>Inſur'gde againſt their maker for his merits.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some angels,<note place="margin">Angels created innocent and pure keepe not their firſt eſtate.</note> gyants like, attempting farre,</l>
               <l>In malice of their founder, male-content,</l>
               <l>Banded themſelues, and made vnciuill warre,</l>
               <l>(Although in vaine) yet with a lewd intent,</l>
               <l>To diſpoſſeſſe him of his regiment:</l>
               <l>Aſpiring Impes, ſo reared vp would wring,</l>
               <l>The crowne and ſcepter from their Lord and king.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their Lord and king als preſt, with armed hands,</l>
               <l>Swift to encounter ſuch vſurping mights,</l>
               <l>Gunnes out his thunder at thoſe fier brands:</l>
               <l>And for reuenge of ſuch rebellious wights,</l>
               <l>He throwes them down, &amp; makes them curſed ſprights:</l>
               <l>Downe in the aire, or in ſome other place:</l>
               <l>For all is hell, whence God withdrawes his face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This rakehell rout inchaunted with diſdaine,<note place="margin">Euill ſprights.</note>
               </l>
               <l>(Now diueliſh feends by lewd apoſtaſie)</l>
               <l>Can make no braggs of any purchaſd gaine,</l>
               <l>But this: they tooke the longitude: how high,</l>
               <l>The heauens be diſtant from hels cuſtodie:</l>
               <l>By their ambitious iumpe, they tooke the meaſure</l>
               <l>Of heauen from hell: but forfeited the pleaſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:11253:19"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet Sathan and his rablement,</l>
               <l>No whit amended by this ouerthrowe;</l>
               <l>Increaſe in rage, and graceles hardiment,</l>
               <l>As faſt as vnto them their torments growe:</l>
               <l>Like to the Lizards, which by many a blowe</l>
               <l>Diſmembred: yet they fiercely turne againe,</l>
               <l>And ſhew their liuely rage in dying paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Since which reuolt, this prince vſurping power,</l>
               <l>Amidſt the aire, hath made nor truce nor peace</l>
               <l>With mightie <hi>Ioue:</hi> but ſtudies euerie hower,</l>
               <l>How he may cauſe the memorie to ceaſe</l>
               <l>Of Gods great acts deſeruing onely praiſe:</l>
               <l>Preſt to ſupplant the Church of Gods owne planting:</l>
               <l>And glad to ſee Gods glorie ſhould be wanting.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He bends his force, to taint the perfect head,</l>
               <l>And rend it from the bodie militant:</l>
               <l>The kingly guide from citie to miſlead,<note place="margin">The deuils aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults againſt Chriſt the head and men the members.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And plant himſelfe therein predominant:</l>
               <l>The pilote of the ſhip he ſtriues to daunt:</l>
               <l>For from the Church, (Chriſts bodie) would he wring,</l>
               <l>Euen Chriſt that head, that pilote, and that king.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſith Gods euerlaſting maieſtie</l>
               <l>Is ſafely ſeated, in his loftie throne:</l>
               <l>Which, neither force, nor threats can terrifie,</l>
               <l>Nor ladder ſcale, nor canon plaie vpon:</l>
               <l>But all their blaſts, themſelues are ouerblowne:</l>
               <l>For howſoeuer buzie ſathan tampares:</l>
               <l>His darts rebounde againſt Gods heauenly rampares.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:11253:20"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore deſpairing to ſurpriſe the head</l>
               <l>Againſt the members, now he turnes his darts:</l>
               <l>He leaues the tree, but would the branches ſhred:</l>
               <l>For neither huntſman hath ſo many arts;</l>
               <l>Nor fiſher plaies ſo many cunning parts;</l>
               <l>Nor fouler laies ſo many craftie gins,</l>
               <l>To catch their ſeu'rall games: as he laies ſins.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As he laies ſins, and baiteth ſecret hookes,</l>
               <l>To catch as well the ſimple as the wiſe:</l>
               <l>The frolike yonker rouing in his lookes,</l>
               <l>He charmes with ſhowes: alluring firſt his eies:</l>
               <l>For greedie pikes he baits with golden flies:</l>
               <l>And princelie ſtate he taketh as an angle,</l>
               <l>The high aſpiring climber to entangle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such as diſdaine the worldlie blaſe of riches,</l>
               <l>With hundred vaine conceits he doth diſtract:</l>
               <l>In maske of truth minds zealouſe he bewitches,</l>
               <l>Obtruding ſhowes, and words for vertues act:</l>
               <l>In all good matters is his poiſon packt:</l>
               <l>And like a canker goodlie fruits and wholſome,</l>
               <l>He blaſts with venime, making al things foulſome.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who could withſtand the gloſing fallacies,</l>
               <l>Of this night prince in malice ſo profound,</l>
               <l>That he can ſlip into dumbe images</l>
               <l>Of gold, or wood, late hewen from the ground:</l>
               <l>And make them yeeld ſome liuelie ſpeech-like ſound:</l>
               <l>Which can aſſume a prophets countenance:</l>
               <l>Cauſe bonefires burne with hidden maintenance.<note place="margin">The continuall fire of <hi>vesta.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:11253:20"/>
            <lg>
               <l>The virgin prophetiſſe of Cumes or Delph,<note place="margin">Oracles <hi>Sibilla.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>He prompted with their anſwere of foreſight:</l>
               <l>He raiſde a <hi>Samuel,</hi> ſhaped like himſelfe,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 28.14.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Which told the king of doomes that hapned right:</l>
               <l>And yet not <hi>Samuel,</hi> but a curſed ſpright.</l>
               <l>He ſtrucke <hi>Ioue Ammons</hi> prieſt with fits of woodnes:</l>
               <l>Suggeſting hurtfull lies, in ſhowe of goodnes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who can deſcrie this great deceiuers guile?<note place="margin">Falſe miracles.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Which could tranſmute a rod into a ſnake?<note place="margin">Exod. 7.12.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Which did conuert the watrie poole of Nile,<note place="margin">Ca. 7.22.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To pulpe bloud? which for a ſhift could make,</l>
               <l>Great ſwarmes of frogs produc'de from eu'rie lake,<note place="margin">Ca. 3.7.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To crawle about the chambers of the king:</l>
               <l>All by his forged Magike practiſing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And, as he is a ſpright inuiſible,</l>
               <l>So can he ſincke the thoughts of mightie ſtates:</l>
               <l>And grope their minds, though he inſenſible,<note place="margin">The deuils know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Till he acquaint himſelfe with their debates,</l>
               <l>And priuate grudges: whence obſeruing dates,</l>
               <l>With long experiments, he takes a veiw:</l>
               <l>For tatling thence what matters ſhall enſue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The braueſt wits, with ſome fantaſtike glimſe,</l>
               <l>Of things to come, he can intoxicate:</l>
               <l>And to inueigle high conceipted impes,</l>
               <l>Of afterclaps he can prognoſticate:</l>
               <l>We ſee men prouident, whoſe weake eſtate,</l>
               <l>No ſooner ſtands, but fals: which liue and die</l>
               <l>The ſelfeſame ſtound, yet what great things they trie;</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:11253:21"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Mens bodies be but ſluggiſh inſtruments,</l>
               <l>Not like to ſprights in actiue motions:</l>
               <l>Yet they by force of mettals, and of plants,</l>
               <l>Produce a thouſand ſtrange concluſions;</l>
               <l>As iſhuing from ſome heauenlie motions:</l>
               <l>And ſhall we thinke, that ſuch old ſoking ſprights,</l>
               <l>Cannot worke woonders farre aboue their mights?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The rather for their immortalitie,</l>
               <l>Plodding in ſchoole of long experience:</l>
               <l>They can diſcouer eu'rie qualitie</l>
               <l>Of hidden ſimples, and ingredients:</l>
               <l>For bodies they haue none to clog the ſence:</l>
               <l>But whatſoeuer enterpriſe entended;</l>
               <l>Within a moment they can haue it ended.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not that they haue the bridle on their necks,</l>
               <l>Alwaies to ruſh,<note place="margin">The deuil bridled of God.</note> and reuell where they luſt:</l>
               <l>Or making hauocke on the earth plaie reaques:</l>
               <l>And tyrannize, with danger and diſtruſt,</l>
               <l>On leud mens ſoules, and bodies of the iuſt:</l>
               <l>But they are muſled, with a greater force:</l>
               <l>At whoſe commaund they take, or ſtaie the courſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not without leaue, that maſter ſpright of lyars,</l>
               <l>Could play the meſſenger to <hi>Achabs</hi> court:<note place="margin">2. King. 22.35.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And by falſe tales, intiſe him to the briars,</l>
               <l>And make him dare his foe, from out his fort:</l>
               <l>Till his owne godles ſoule returned ſhort.</l>
               <l>Nor yet without a paſſe-port to him graunted,</l>
               <l>Could humble <hi>Iob,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.15.</note> with ſuch aſſaults be haunted:</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:11253:21"/>
            <lg>
               <l>His varlets ſlaine, his riches all deſtroide,</l>
               <l>His flocks conſumde, his camels made a praie:</l>
               <l>His kinred ſit aloofe, as men annoide</l>
               <l>With ſuch a poore baſe kinſman in their waie:</l>
               <l>His houſe turnd topſie turuie to decaie:</l>
               <l>This was not done but by commiſſion:</l>
               <l>The deuill making firſt petition.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Eternall <hi>Ioue</hi> to proue the confidence</l>
               <l>Of conſtant men, that faith might grow by triall:</l>
               <l>And choke with errors the erronious ſence,</l>
               <l>That in true matters there be no eſpiall:</l>
               <l>To lying ſprights he maketh not deniall,</l>
               <l>But lets them ſlip, which do not ceaſe to further</l>
               <l>The leud attempts commenc'd in <hi>Adams</hi> murther.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Still they purſue, and practiſe wonted feates:</l>
               <l>The ſelfe ſame anuill they do hammer ſtill,</l>
               <l>And forge new ſleights, like to their old deceits:</l>
               <l>But yet ſomtimes, do good againſt their will.</l>
               <l>And though the rout apoſtate ſeeke to kill,</l>
               <l>Yet ſomtime they vnawres, in midſt of bloud,</l>
               <l>Haue made fierce tirants confort with the good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The hurtles hoſt, Gods euerlaſting traine,</l>
               <l>Which kept their firſt eſtate, ſaunce hautie pride:<note place="margin">Good angels.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Not mounting vp, nor tumbling downe againe,</l>
               <l>Attend Gods pleaſure, ſtarting not aſide,</l>
               <l>But tread the pathes, prefixed by their guide:</l>
               <l>This is their onlie delectation:</l>
               <l>Gods glorie, and the ſaints ſaluation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:11253:22"/>
               <l>No ſtrange deſire aſſailes their phantaſie:</l>
               <l>The pleaſant aſpect of almightie God</l>
               <l>Is better then the ſweeteſt Ambroſie:</l>
               <l>The retriue of a lambe, that long hath trod</l>
               <l>In wailes deſert, looſlie ſtraide abroad:</l>
               <l>The child once loſt, reduc'de to penitence:</l>
               <l>Delighteth them as <hi>Nectars</hi> influence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nought elſe requires the high aſpiring minde,</l>
               <l>But kingdome vnto kingdome to vnite;</l>
               <l>And Diademe with Diademe to binde,</l>
               <l>That all the world might ſtoupe to one mans might:</l>
               <l>But heauenly angels haue no ſuch delight,</l>
               <l>No ſuch deſire of greater excellence</l>
               <l>But in Gods ſeruice ſpend their diligence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No ſooner ſounds the voice of Gods command:</l>
               <l>No ſooner doth a becke of maieſtie proceed:</l>
               <l>No ſooner comes a matter to be ſcand,</l>
               <l>Wherein theſe angels ſerue in any ſteed,</l>
               <l>But out they flie with more than winged ſpeed:</l>
               <l>Bending themſelues to execute the word,</l>
               <l>And to effect the mandate of their Lord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One of them followes <hi>Agar</hi> in hir flight,</l>
               <l>And ſhortning hir exiled pilgrimage,<note place="margin">Goneſ. 21.17.</note>
               </l>
               <l>By ſpeech doth yeeld vnlooked for delight:</l>
               <l>Another doth conduct with aequipage,<note place="margin">Exod. 23.23. cap. 33.2.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The marching armies of Gods heritage:</l>
               <l>Others direct yoong <hi>Iacob</hi> to the Eaſt,</l>
               <l>And yeelde him courage in his firſt nights reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:11253:22"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Another skilde in Phyſicks lore applies</l>
               <l>A ſoueraigne plaiſter for decaied ſight,<note place="margin">Tob. 11.7.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Euen ſuch as vnto faithfull <hi>Tobiths</hi> eies</l>
               <l>Reſtord againe the long deſired light.</l>
               <l>To Nazareth one takes his nimble flight,</l>
               <l>And therefore truth to <hi>Marie</hi> doth pronounce,<note place="margin">Lue. 1.26.</note>
               </l>
               <l>She ſhould be Maide and Mother all at once:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She ſhould conceaue, and beare but onely one:</l>
               <l>Yet at one burden ſhould ſhe bring forth theſe,</l>
               <l>A Father, Husband, Brother, and a Sonne,</l>
               <l>That by this birth men troubled might finde eaſe:</l>
               <l>When as the of-ſpring, whom it ſo did pleaſe</l>
               <l>To be incloſde within hir virgins wombe,</l>
               <l>Might not be cowpd within a world of roeme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Another ſort in feruent zeale attend,</l>
               <l>With hand, and foote to guarde the tempted ſonne:</l>
               <l>And Sathans conflict brought vnto an end,<note place="margin">Matth. 4.11.</note>
               </l>
               <l>They miniſter him comfort that had wonne,</l>
               <l>And helpe to triumph when the combats done:</l>
               <l>In fruitles ſand, and ſtonie wildernes,</l>
               <l>They do not leaue Chriſt comfortles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One cheares him vp to take the bitter chalice,</l>
               <l>And drinke that off which God had tempered,<note place="margin">Lue. 22.43.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To waſh from ſinne, and wring from Sathans malice</l>
               <l>The ſoules of men by Sathan blemiſhed:</l>
               <l>Another brings glad tydings of the dead,<note place="margin">Math. 28.2.5.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And ſhewes the Matrones of their Chriſts ariſing,</l>
               <l>Which was reputed dead, by their ſurmiſing.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:11253:23"/>
            <lg>
               <l>One far beyond all expectation</l>
               <l>Brings tidings of <hi>Iohns</hi> ſtrange natiuitie:<note place="margin">Luk. 1.13.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Another puts in execution</l>
               <l>The tenor of Gods purpoſe faithfully,</l>
               <l>Aduancing Iſraels herde to dignitie.<note place="margin">Exod. 3.2.</note>
               </l>
               <l>One makes a fearfull ſlaughter and a ſad,</l>
               <l>On all the firſt borne males that Aegypt had.<note place="margin">Exod. 12.29.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Exempted onely from the maſſaker,</l>
               <l>All ſuch as had their doore poſts painted red,</l>
               <l>With bloud of lambe ſlaine for the paſſeouer:</l>
               <l>Another in a moment vanquiſhed</l>
               <l>The hoſt of <hi>Rabſache,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Kings. 19.35.</note> who thundered</l>
               <l>Blaſphemous words, and termes of higheſt ſlander,</l>
               <l>Boaſting his gods, againſt the heauens commander.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His ſoldiers had ſubdude the Eaſterlings:</l>
               <l>And now begirt that citie, which alone</l>
               <l>Adores the onelie peerleſſe king of kings:</l>
               <l>Without the wals ſcarſe could a bird haue flowne,</l>
               <l>For troupes beleagaring the garriſon.</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Ezechias</hi> viewing, as a prince moſt wiſe,</l>
               <l>Foreſees th'euent, as preſent to his eies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Foreſees the common hauocke round about:</l>
               <l>His ſubiects taken captiue, caſt in bands,</l>
               <l>Their tender children ſquatted in the rout:</l>
               <l>Their noble virgins forc'de with bloodie hands,</l>
               <l>Deſlowr'de with rauiſhment, and rough commands:</l>
               <l>His kinglie perſon eide with thouſand threats,</l>
               <l>Alreadie hackt and hewd in their conceats.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:11253:23"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Foreſees the naked temple ſtript of wall,</l>
               <l>The ſacred Cenſors not with mirrhe perfumde,</l>
               <l>The Altar bare, no ſacrifice at all,</l>
               <l>But prieſts of God, and prieſthood both conſumde:</l>
               <l>Waighing theſe things, and how his foe ſtill fumde,</l>
               <l>He ſprinkled aſhes, and with penitence,</l>
               <l>He cride to God in ſackcloth, for defence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>God heares his crie, and whets his lightning darts,</l>
               <l>To ſtrike the ſquadrons of that heathniſh rout:</l>
               <l>And while dead ſleepe benums their ſenſeleſſe harts:</l>
               <l>(Their bodies, hemming in the fires about)</l>
               <l>He doth addreſſe and ſend a champion out:</l>
               <l>Hunting the fruſtrate legar without pitie,</l>
               <l>And caſting friendly lookes vpon the citie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Charg'd is the field, a ſcowre flies out the dart,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſingle flight is not content to make</l>
               <l>A ſingle ſlaughter: but through cu'rie part</l>
               <l>It cuts a lane, and thickeſt troupes doth take:</l>
               <l>Embrewd in bloud, and like a lightning flake,</l>
               <l>The ſword doth brandiſh, lighting here and there,</l>
               <l>As doth a whirlewind whiske about the aire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They flie in chaſe, but too too ſlow they drag,</l>
               <l>To ſcape the reach of ſuch a ramping blade:</l>
               <l>The glittring ſteele is onelie ſeene to wag,</l>
               <l>By which, ſuch hauocke in one night is made:</l>
               <l>Like as the windmill ſailes with ſowpe vnſtaid,</l>
               <l>Do ſwindge about, yet no man ſees the winde,</l>
               <l>By whoſe impulſiue force, the ſailes do grinde.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:11253:24"/>
            <lg>
               <l>No ſooner had the purple morning chac'de</l>
               <l>The donker ſhade, from haughtie Liban's top,</l>
               <l>But th'Ebrew garders in their ſconſes plac'de,</l>
               <l>Behold whole heapes of men ſlaine at a chop,</l>
               <l>(An hundred, foure ſcore, and fiue thouſand) ſtop</l>
               <l>And peſter all their wonted paſſages:</l>
               <l>As erſt with men, ſo now with carcaſes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Iewes reare ſolemne triumph to the skie,</l>
               <l>Inſulting on the quailed conquerour:</l>
               <l>Aſcribing honor for this victorie,</l>
               <l>Alone vnto the worlds chiefe gouernour,</l>
               <l>Which gaue theſe brauing troupes the ouerture.</l>
               <l>But you O ſacred tutors of the ſaints,<note place="margin">Epilog with a conuerſion to the Angels.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Swift archers helping when our armie faints.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You that in counſell are as delegates,</l>
               <l>And poſts in needfull expedition:</l>
               <l>Heraulds in ſounding out to all eſtates</l>
               <l>The ſumme of Gods decreed commiſſion:</l>
               <l>You that do feare the countenance of none:</l>
               <l>Were men like rocks, or ſturdie like to giants,</l>
               <l>You dare preſume to giue them all defiance.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Faithfull interpreters from God to men:</l>
               <l>Faine would I ſtill attend vpon your trace,</l>
               <l>With laggring pinions of my feeble pen,</l>
               <l>But that I iourney to a further place,</l>
               <l>And therefore doubt, leaſt in ſo long a race,</l>
               <l>Haſting too much, the firſt outſetting day,</l>
               <l>My raſh attempt might faulter by the way.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:11253:24"/>
            <lg>
               <l>For he that entertaines a braue deſire,</l>
               <l>(Which well beſeemes a woorthie Caualeer)</l>
               <l>To view ſtrange men, ſtrange maners and attire,</l>
               <l>In forren countries as a traueller,</l>
               <l>It bootes him not to be ſwift paſſenger:</l>
               <l>He ſpeedes it well if in his firſt daies rode,</l>
               <l>He leaues the place and coaſt of his abode.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
